Guide to the Carr Family Collection of Travel Sketches, Scrapbooks, and Genealogical Material
Yale Center for British Art, Rare Books and Manuscripts
Carr family collection of travel sketches, scrapbooks, and genealogical material
1699-1981
1811-1899
MSS 8
Yale Center for British Art, Rare Books and Manuscripts
10
The collection comprises travel sketches, scrapbooks, and genealogical material concerning the Carr family of Northumberland, England.
Carr family
Carr, Anna Margaret, 1797-1872
Carr, Thomas William, 1830-1912
Lushington, Sarah Grace, 1794-1837
Hogg, James, 1770-1835 ( Raid of the Kers)
Carr, Ralph Edward, 1833-1892 ( History of the family of Carr of Dunston Hill, Co. Durham)
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Arrangement
Arranged in four series: I. Sketchbooks, 1811-1863; II. Scrapbooks, 1699-1981; III. Family history and genealogy, 1823-1912; IV. Photographs, etc.
Scope and Contents
The collection comprises travel sketches, scrapbooks, and genealogical material concerning the Carr family of Northumberland, England. The Reverend Thomas William Carr (1830-1912) appears to have played a key role in compiling the material, especially genealogical items.
The collection documents the burgeoning of interest in local and family history in the nineteenth century, as reflected by the thorough efforts of the Rev. Thomas William Carr to collect information and physical items relating to the history of the Carr family; the travels and artistic works of two Victorian women, Anna Margaret Carr (who traveled to Europe and India) and her sister Sarah Grace Carr (who focused on local English themes), whose numerous landscape sketches can be used to reconstruct their travel itineraries and provide insights to their interests as both travelers and artists; the often overlooked but pivotal role of Geneva and other Calvinist areas as stops on the Grand Tour (especially for English travelers); Victorian decorative arts, as seen in the greeting and note cards from the period preserved in the collection; and the religious attitudes, daily social life, and business interests of a nineteenth century Anglican clergyman, as reflected in the journals and correspondence of the Rev. Thomas William Carr.
Biographical / Historical
The Carr family was originally based in Northumberland and became particularly prominent in Newcastle. It included several prominent branches. The Carr family of Woodhall and Hexam can be traced to John Carr, a yeoman who lived c. 1450-1515. From here the family spread to Kibblesworth and Newcastle and then to Dunston Hill in Durham. The notable businessman Ralph Carr, who made a fortune in the eighteenth century in the Newcastle area through merchant and trading activities, was a member of this branch of the family and acquired a sizeable fortune which he partially used to build an estate at Hedgeley in Northumberland for the family.
Another branch of the family settled in Hetton and traces their roots to William Carr who, in 1412, was a notable landowner in Northumberland. This branch of the family eventually acquired Castle Ford and lived there for several generations.
The final major branch of the family settled at Eshott Heugh and Frognal. It is this branch of the Carr family that concerns most of the material in the present collection.
The Carr family history is richly treated in: The History of the Family of Carr of Dunston Hill, County Durham, and the Collateral Lines in England by Colonel Ralph Edward Carr and Cuthbert Ellison Carr (London: Mitchell and Hughes, 1893-99)--an annotated copy of which is available in the present collection.
Thomas Carr (1733-1793) The patriarch of the line of Carrs based at Eshott Heugh lived from 1733-1793. He traveled to Georgia as a child and was a Sub-Officer of the Marines. In this capacity he participated in the siege of Havana. With four different wives, Carr produced four sons (Mark William Carr, a soldier, Thomas William, a lawyer, William Ogle, a sailor, and John Thomas, a merchant) and two daughters (Ann and Rebecca). Thomas Carr was very reckless with the family finances and nearly obliterated their wealth and landholdings. His son, Thomas William, however, managed to retain Eshott Heugh.
Thomas William Carr (1770-1829) Carr records that he was born on 19 March 1770 in Savannah, Georgia and that he and his family returned to England in 1772. He trained as a lawyer and married Frances Morton in 1794. He appears to have been very industrious and worked to rebuild the family fortune. He was called to the Bar in 1801 and made Solicitor of Excise in 1805. Carr was described as "thoroughly a family man," who took great joy in spending time with his wife and children. He had eight children: Sarah Grace (1794-1837), Frances Rebecca (called Fanny) (1796-1880), Anna Margaret (1797-1872), Thomas William (1801-1840), Andrew Morton (1799-1852), William Ogle (1802-1856), Isabella (1804-1860) and Laura Carr (1807-1868). He died suddenly from a "rupture of the septum of the heart" at Frognal on 27 April 1829.
Sarah Grace Lushington (Carr) (1794-1837) Sarah was born in London on 6 December 1794. The family history records that in 1810 she was travelling in Italy and Switzerland and so it appears she also, like her sister Anna Margaret, took a Grand Tour of sorts. A letter from her father survives asking her to translate a Latin poem for him, and she appears to have been reasonably well-educated. On 8 August 1821 she married Dr. Stephen Lushington, the son of the Director of the East India Company. She became a close friend of Lady Byron (whom Stephen Lushington represented in her separation from Lord Byron). Sarah and Stephen had five sons and five daughters and she died on 20 September 1837. According to the DNB, her last illness was harrowing and it deeply moved her husband. After her death, her sister Frances kept house for her husband until her own death. Aunt Fanny Carr was regarded as somewhat severe and harsh but she displayed a great love for all her nieces and nephews and lived until 1880. Sarah's husband Stephen had an important legal career as a judge, a Member of Parliament, and an anti-slavery activist. He also represented Queen Caroline in her trial by Parliament to have her crown and status as the wife of George IV stripped from her on grounds of her adultery. His defense of her was successful and she remained in contact with him until her death, naming him as the executor of her will. Of the couple's children, Edward Harbord Lushington (1822–1904), became a senior Indian civil servant; Vernon Lushington (1832–1912), a county court judge; and Godfrey Lushington (1832–1907), Vernon's twin, permanent under-secretary in the Home Office.
Anna Margaret Carr (1797-1872) Anna was born in London on 13 December 1797. Notes in the family's Bible record that she was inoculated for smallpox in 1798. In 1833 her brother William was appointed to a diplomatic position in Ceylon and she travelled there with him. She returned to London when her brother married in 1836 and spent the rest of her life living with various family members until her death on 9 March 1872. According to biographical notes on her, "she was devoted to natural history, and was especially proficient in botany. Her quick and gifted pencil has left her relations quite a gallery of interesting sketches … her chief sketches were bits of scenery in places where she stayed, and with a few but very telling touches the effect produced was singularly graceful."
Rev. Thomas William Carr (1801-1840) Son of Thomas William Carr. He passed his divinity school requirements in the 1820s and was licensed to serve as a cleric in the county of Rutland in 1825, thereafter becoming Curate of St. Michael's in Bristol, and of Teddington. In 1829 he married Susan Hamilton (née Woodward) (d. 1834), to whom was born their children Thomas William Carr (later of Barming) (b. 1830), Lucy Emily (1832-1888), and Francis Culling Carr (b. 1834). After Susan's death, Rev. Thomas William Carr married Joanna Maria Childers in 1837.
Laura Carr (1807-1868) Daughter of Thomas William Carr (b. 1770). In 1850 she married Sir Robert Monsey Rolfe (1790-1868), who was raised to the peerage as Baron Cranworth the same year, and served as Lord Chancellor from 1852-1858 and 1865-1866. The couple had no children. In the Rev. T.W. Carr Scrapbook (Oversize 7), there is a letter from Arthur Bigge in 1895 referring to correspondence between Her Majesty and the family of Lord and Lady Cranworth. Bigge writes that "The Queen was very fond of Lady Cranworth."
Rev. Thomas William Carr (1830-1912) Thomas William Carr was the son of the Rev. Thomas William Carr (the brother of Sarah Grace and Anna Margaret Carr) and his wife Susan. He was the grandson of Thomas William Carr of Eshott Heugh, the family patriarch and son of Thomas Carr. He was born on 14 July 1830 and earned his BA from Wadham College, Oxford in 1853. He followed this with an MA in 1854 and was ordained a deacon in 1856 and a priest in 1857. In 1865 he became the rector of Barming in Kent and was also recognized as an English Chaplain of Bordighera, Italy. Carr and his wife Harriet had seven children: Mary Joanna Sophia (1859); Thomas William (1861); Robert Lancelot (1863); Alured John Deacon (1866); Laura (1868); Frank Collett (1870); Margaret Lucy (1871). Upon the death of his wife, he was remarried (in 1891) to Emily Maria Charlotte, herself a widow.
Harriet Carr (Deacon) (1829-1889) Harriet Carr was the wife of the editor, Rev. Thomas William Carr, and predeceased him on 21 February 1889. In her obituary, reprinted in the Carr family history, she is described as living "a life of usefulness" and as "loving and loved by all her husband's relations, and winning golden opinions in the parish." She is also described as loving plain needlework and working industriously within the parish (undertaking such activities as teaching Sunday school each week). Prior to her death she had suffered six years of illness, mostly associated with her lungs and, despite her trips to Nice and Bordighera to recover her strength, she became increasingly sick.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Acquired 2009, Paul Mellon Fund.
Grand tours (Education); Women artists -- Great Britain; Women travelers -- Great Britain; Northumberland (England) -- History; Northumberland (England) -- Social life and customs; Pisa (Italy) -- Pictorial works; Diaries; Genealogies; Scrapbooks; Sketchbooks; Landscape drawings; Views; Travel sketches -- Europe; Travel sketches -- France; Travel sketches -- Great Britain; Travel sketches -- Italy; Travel sketches -- Switzerland; Charcoal drawings; Engravings; Graphite drawings; Photographs; Wash drawings; Watercolors; Chron -- 1824-1899; Carr family; Carr family -- Heraldry; Carr, Anna Margaret, 1797-1872; Carr, Harriet, 1829-1889; Carr, Thomas William, 1830-1912; Cranworth, Robert Monsey Rolfe, Baron, 1790-1868; Cranworth, Laura Rolfe, Lady, 1807-1868; Lushington, Sarah Grace, 1794-1837; Eshott House (Alnwick, England)
- Travel sketches, Series I
  - Album of drawings of Great Britain and the Continent, 1811-1859; Lushington, Sarah Grace, 1794-1837; Carr, Anna Margaret, 1797-1872; 1 volume (81 drawings): graphite, some with watercolor; 32 x 47 cm (Box Oversize 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Album of drawings by Anna Margaret Carr and Sarah Grace Carr. Only three drawings appear to be signed: "Hougoumont, Sept. 21, 1816" (no. 2) and "Salden House, January 26, 1832" (no. 19) are initialed by Anna Margaret, while "Hampstead Heath, Jun. 9, 1815" (no. 57) is initialed "SGC". From this evidence it is difficult to determine which drawings were executed by which sister, especially since the 1816 drawing initialed "AMC" has a very similar style to those that appear to be by SGC. The differences in style among the drawings seem to be attributable more to the age and maturity of the artist than to individual aesthetics, since the earlier drawings are generally more exact, detailed, and stiff; the later drawings are vaguer and done with a blunter pencil.
    Places identified in the drawings include St. Mary's Scilly, Hougoumont, Dover harbor, Delft, Pisa, Nuremberg, Bex, Baveno, Tourtemagne, Edgeworth, Holdenby House, Lowestoft, Tynemouth, Windsor Forest, Hampstead Heath, West End, Hormead Bury, and Tunbridge Wells.
    Great Britain -- Pictorial works; Travel sketches -- Europe; Watercolors; Travel sketches -- Great Britain; Europe -- Pictorial works; Graphite drawings
  - Drawings of Great Britain and Atlantic Isles, 1812-1863; Carr, Anna Margaret, 1797-1872; Lushington, Sarah Grace, 1794-1837; 38 drawings: graphite, some with watercolor; 27 x 39 cm, and smaller (Box Oversize 2)
    An unbound set of drawings, most of which are mounted on heavier paper stock. A small label on the original paper covers reads "My mother's and aunt Anna's drawings." Only two of the sketches are signed: Easby Abbey is signed "SGL" (Sarah Grace Lushington); "Westhumble" is labeled "Aunt Anna". Presumably, the drawings include a mix of work by Anna Margaret Carr and Sarah Grace Carr Lushington.
    Included are sketches of Mount Batten, Dorking, Tunbridge Wells, Hampstead Heath, Kirkby, Fountains Abbey, Easby Abbey, and Duddingston Loch. There also a few drawings of locations outside the British Isles, including Berne, Bodenbach, Madeira, Mauritius, and St. Helena.
    Graphite drawings; Travel sketches -- Great Britain; Watercolors; Great Britain -- Pictorial works
  - Album of drawings of France and Switzerland, 1824; Carr, Anna Margaret, 1797-1872; 1 volume (69 drawings): graphite, some with watercolor; 38 x 54 cm (Box Oversize 3)
    Labeled on the spine "Vol. 1 1824". Comprises sketches from Anna Margaret Carr's Grand Tour, in France and Switzerland. The sketches begin on 22 August 1824 near Montreuil. Carr traveled for five weeks from Paris to Florence (first going north-east through Reims via Soissons, then south through Geneva via Dijon and Poligny, and finally along the northern shore of Lake Geneva through Lausanne). The first volume ends on 8 September 1824 at Saint Maurice.
    Graphite drawings; Grand tours (Education); Watercolors; Switzerland -- Pictorial works; France -- Pictorial works; Travel sketches -- Switzerland; Travel sketches -- France
  - Album of drawings of Switzerland and Italy, 1824; Carr, Anna Margaret, 1797-1872; 1 volume (67 drawings): graphite, some with watercolor; 38 x 54 cm (Box Oversize 4)
    A continuation of the previous sketchbook, labeled on the spine "II Vol 1824". Carr's Grand Tour continues on 9 Sept 1824 at Tourtemagne (Turtmann, Switzerland). She crosses through Simplon Pass in early September and moves southeast towards Como, south to Genoa, and spends the last week of September traveling east along the Mediterranean, with sketches concentrated in La Spezia, Livorno, Pisa, and Florence.
    Switzerland -- Pictorial works; Travel sketches -- Switzerland; Italy -- Pictorial works; Graphite drawings; Travel sketches -- Italy; Grand tours (Education); Watercolors
  - Album of drawings of France and Italy, 1827; Carr, Anna Margaret, 1797-1872; 1 volume (63 drawings): graphite, some with watercolor; 32 x 47 cm (Box Oversize 5)
    Labeled "Foreign Sketches 1827" on the spine. This album seems to record the start of Anna Margaret Carr's 1827-8 voyage to the Continent, beginning near Paris (the first labeled sketch is in Montreuil, France, on 7 September 1827) and tracing her voyage southeast into Italy and eventually to Pisa, where the sketchbook ends in November 1827 (though she remained there through early 1828).
    The drawings are pasted into the album in rough chronological order. In her first week near Paris, Anna Margaret visited Abbeville and St. Germain. She spent two weeks traveling southeast toward the Italian border, visiting Auxerre, Autun, Chalon-sur-Saône, Lyons, Les Echelles, Aiguebelle, Montmeillant, and various places in Savoy (including Saint-Michel-de-Maurienne, "Lans le Bourg", and Modane) before crossing into Italy.
    In Italy, she traveled southeast along the Mediterranean coast to Sarzana, Spezzia and the "Mountains of Carara" (Carrara, the source of Michelangelo's marble) in early October, finally arriving in Pisa, where the album ends. She seems to have arrived in Pisa at some point in mid-October 1827, but some Pisa sketches are dated November as well (the next volume reveals that she stayed in Pisa through the spring).
    Watercolors; Italy -- Pictorial works; Travel sketches -- Italy; Grand tours (Education); Graphite drawings; France -- Pictorial works; Travel sketches -- France
  - Album of drawings of Pisa and vicinity, 1827-1828; Carr, Anna Margaret, 1797-1872; 1 volume (59 drawings): graphite, some with watercolor; 32 x 47 cm (Box Oversize 6)
    Labeled "Foreign Sketches 1828." The album is mostly comprised of drawings from Anna Margaret's travels in and around Pisa from January through April of 1828, but also includes a few from late 1827. The album ends with two drawings from Martigny, Switzerland in May 1828. Aside from these final two, the drawings are pasted into the album in no discernible order.
    Aside from Pisa, places identified in the drawings include Florence (drawn from afar), San Domino, Serchio, Lucca, and La Verucca (in the Valle dei Calci).
    Graphite drawings; Watercolors; Italy -- Pictorial works; Travel sketches -- Italy; Pisa (Italy) -- Pictorial works; Grand tours (Education)
- Scrapbooks, notebooks, and genealogical material, Series II
  - Carr Family scrapbooks, 1699-1890; Carr, Thomas William, 1830-1912; 2 volumes (volume 1 circa 225 pages, volume 2 blank); 53 x 37 cm (Box Oversize 7-8)
    Large bound book labeled "Scrap Book, Vol. I" on the spine. Pages are heavy paper, colored (or discolored?) pinkish, some yellowish. Documents have been pasted, stapled or laid in. First half largely contains legal documents, ordination certificates, passports, etc. from the lives of Thomas William Carr (1770-1829) made Solicitor of Excise in 1805, his son the Reverend Thomas William Carr (1801-1840), Rector of Teddington?, and his son Reverend Thomas William Carr (b. 1830), Rector of Barming. It seems likely the scrapbook was assembled by Rev Thomas William Carr of Barming, and that he collected manuscripts from friends, family, etc. One newspaper clipping, for instance, is reported as having been found in an old cabinet in the Eshott Heugh estate.
    Some of the documents (such as a 1699 lease from the Palatinate of Durham regarding some Carr family properties) have paper or wax seals affixed to them. Others (such as the Confirmation of Arms and Grant of Crest to Gayus Dyxon in 1565) are colored, photolithographed copies of much older documents (photoengraving techniques, pioneered in the 1850s, had developed greatly by 1880).
    The documents don't seem to follow any particular order, although they are grouped more or less by document type and time period. In a very, very rough scheme, the groupings move through:
    (1) Sale of Eshott Heugh estate (2) Documents from lives of Rev Thomas William Carr (of Teddington) and Rev Thomas William Carr (of Barming), including when they were ordained curates, rectors, etc., certificates of examinations passed, declarations of subscribing to the 39 Articles and the Liturgy of the Church of England. Many of these have the Episcopal Seals of various bishops attached (particularly the Bishop of Peterborough and Archbishop of Canterbury). (3) Travel passports allowing travel on the Continent; some sheets seem to have been issued by French government and stamped/signed by notaries or officials of different countries visited. (4) One large, elaborate declaration on vellum headed "George the Third by the Grace of God," apparently appointing Thomas William Carr a Solicitor of the Excise in 1805. (5) Painted images and photolithographed copies of coats of arms and Carr family genealogies (6) "Fac-similes" of historical documents and newspaper articles from historic events (7) Documents surrounding the death of Major Mark William Carr when the steamer General Outram was lost off "Rutnagherry" in India. A Carr Compassion Fund was established in 1871 (?) in Major Carr's honor, to aid police officers' widows. (8) Turn-of-the-century greeting cards, Christmas cards, Valentines, many with colored images and personal messages. (9) Sketches and photos of memorials and sarcophagi of Carr family tombs. Include photos of tombs of William Ogle Carr (Rev TW Carr of Barming's uncle) and Rev Thomas William Carr (of Teddington, labeled "my father's grave," presumably by TW Carr of Barming). Also letters, death notices, etc. regarding Carr family burials. (10) Notecards and engravings of various churches associated with Carr family. (11) Copy of Carr family pedigree.
    Large albums with spine title: "Scrap Book, Vol. I[-II]." Volume II is entirely blank. Some of the documents are affixed to sheets of the album; many others are laid in (on stubs). The first half of the album comprises legal documents, ordination certificates, passports, etc. from the lives of Thomas William Carr (1770-1829) made Solicitor of Excise in 1805, his son the Reverend Thomas William Carr (1801-1840), Rector of Teddington, and his son Reverend Thomas William Carr (b. 1830), Rector of Barming. It seems likely the scrapbook was assembled by Thomas William Carr of Barming, and that he collected the scrapbooks material from from friends and family. One newspaper clipping, for instance, is reported as having been found in an old cabinet in the Eshott Heugh estate.
    Some of the original documents, such as a 1699 lease from the Palatinate of Durham regarding Carr family properties, have paper or wax seals affixed to them. Others, are facsimiles (many photolithographed) of much older documents.
    There is no apparent ordering scheme, although they are grouped very roughly by document type and time period. These groupings include the following:
    Sale of the Eshott Heugh estate.
    Documents from lives of Thomas William Carr (of Teddington) and Thomas William Carr (of Barming), including items concerning their ordinations as curates, rectors, etc., certificates of examinations passed, and declarations subscribing to the 39 Articles and the Liturgy of the Church of England. Many of these have the Episcopal seals of various bishops (particularly the Bishop of Peterborough and Archbishop of Canterbury).
    Passports allowing travel on the Continent. Some sheets seem to have been issued by the French government.
    One large, elaborate declaration on vellum headed "George the Third by the Grace of God," apparently appointing Thomas William Carr a Solicitor of the Excise in 1805.
    Carr family coats of arms (originals and copies), and Carr family genealogies.
    Facsimiles of historical documents and newspaper articles from historic events.
    Documents concerning the death of Major Mark William Carr when the steamer General Outram was lost off "Rutnagherry" in India. A Carr Compassion Fund was established in 1871 (?) in Major Carr's honor, to aid police officers' widows.
    Turn-of-the-century greeting cards, Christmas cards, and Valentines, many with colored images and personal messages.
    Sketches and photos of memorials and sarcophagi of Carr family tombs. Include photos of tombs of William Ogle Carr (the uncle of T.W. Carr of Barming) and Thomas William Carr (of Teddington). Also present are letters, death notices, etc., regarding Carr family burials.
    Notecards and engravings of various churches associated with the Carr family.
    Copy of the Carr family pedigree.
    Scrapbooks; Passports; Greeting cards; Sarcophagi; Clergy -- Great Britain; Eshott House (Alnwick, England); Carr, Thomas, 1733-1793; Carr, Thomas William, 1830-1912; Carr family; Carr, Thomas William, 1830-1912